<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King Iames by the grace of God, king of England, Scotland, France and Ireland ... : whereas our late sister ... Elizabeth late queen of England by her letters patents bearing date at Westminster the xiii. day of Iuly, in the xxxvi. yeere of her raigne ...</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22015</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8376</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3659</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33150704</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33150704</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28718</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22015)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28718)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1875:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King Iames by the grace of God, king of England, Scotland, France and Ireland ... : whereas our late sister ... Elizabeth late queen of England by her letters patents bearing date at Westminster the xiii. day of Iuly, in the xxxvi. yeere of her raigne ...</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>5 leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>For granting 21-year patent to the Duke of Lenox, for the office of King's Alnager, collector of the subsidy on wool cloth.</note>
                  <note>Other title information from first 5 lines of text.</note>
                  <note>"Witnesse Our selfe at Westminster, the sixteenth day of September, in the third yeere of Our Reigne of England, Fraunce and Ireland, and of Scotland the nine and thirtieth."</note>
                  <note>Signed: Clapham. Per bre. depriuat. Sigil.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Richmond, Ludovic Stuart, --  Duke of, 1574-1624.</term>
               <term>Wool fabrics --  Taxation --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Monopolies --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:28718:1"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>AMES, by the grace of God, king of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</signed> 
               <salute>To al men to whom theſe Our preſent Letters ſhall come, Greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">The recitail of the late Queenes Letters Patents by her granted to Sir George Delues and William Fitz-william.</note> Wheras our late Siſter of famous Memorie, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> late Queen of <hi>England,</hi> by her Letters Patents, bearing date at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the xiii. day of <hi>Iuly,</hi> in the xxxvi. yeere of her Raigne: Reciting thereby, that whereas it had beene alwayes of ancient time, and ſo from time to time thought and found very profitable for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth of this Realme, That all manner woollen cloth made within this ſame Realme to be ſold, ſhould be ſearched, meaſured and ſealed by the <hi>Alnagers</hi> of her Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors, and of her Highnes being Officers to that purpoſe, appointed to the intent, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well that no perſon ſhould bee deceiued, by buying deceitfull woollen cloth vnduely made, As alſo that by reaſon of the true making of the ſaid woollen Cloth, the making thereof might be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And the people of this Realme therby the better ſet on worke. <note n="(b)" place="margin">Thought fit and reaſonable that a reaſonable fee ſhould bee paid to the Alna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for his paines.</note> And that it had likewiſe beene thought and found very reaſonable and neceſſary, that a reaſonable fee ſhould be paide vnto the ſaide Alnager, for his paines in that behalfe: And that a Subſidie ſhould be paid for the ſaid Clothes, vnto her ſaid Progenitors, and her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And to that end, that diuers Acts of Parliaments and Ordinances, had beene made in the time of her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors, and were then in force. And that for aſmuch as then of late yeeres, diuers ſorts of woollen Clothes, and other commodities commonly called double, middle and ſingle Bayes, Raſhe, or Stammell of Florence ſort, Serge of Frence ſort, Sayes of Flaunders ſort, Narrow worſteeds, Grograynes, Mockadoes of euery ſortes, Plumets, Freezadoes, Carrel, Fuſtian of Naples, Blankets, called Spanniſh Rugges, Knithoſe of worſted yarne, and of all ſorts of new Draperies, and other new Stuffes, and commodities, then made of wooll onely, or moſt part of wooll, had been chiefly deuiſed, &amp; made within her Realme of England by Strangers, &amp; Aliens borne, that reſorted into this Realme. <note n="(c)" place="margin">That all new ſorts of Draperies by Statutes ought to be ſearched, weighed and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and charged with a Subſidie in ſuch ſort as other woollen clothes.</note> And that then of later time, the making was vſed in diuers places within this Realme, aſwell by the ſaide ſtrangers, as by her Subiects, which new ſortes of Draperies, and woollen commoditities with all other like that ſhould be therafter inuented, or deuiſed to be made wholly, or moſt part of wooll within this Realme, ought by the Statutes, Lawes and Ordinances of this Realme, and by the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and equitie of the ſame, to be ſearched and meaſured or weighed, and ſealed, and to be charged with a Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, to be paide to her Maieſtie, her heires and ſucceſſors in ſuch ſort, as other woollen clothes before that time ſold or made within this Realme of England: had beene and ought to be. And that no Officer or Officers were eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally appointed, either to the ſearching, meaſuring, weighing and ſealing of the ſaid new Draperies, or to the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of the ſaid Subſidie, vntill that then of late yeeres. her truſtie ſeruants, Sir <hi>George Delues,</hi> Knight, and <hi>William Fitz william,</hi> two other Maieſties Gentlemen Pentioners, had beene thereunto appointed, by her ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Leaſes, which then were expired and determined: By reaſon whereof, not onely the ſaid newly deuiſed Clothes, and woollen commodities had wanted, and might againe want the due allowance that ought to haue beene, and was by the ſealing thereof, to the daunger of the buyers of the ſame. But alſo that her ſaid late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie had likewiſe wanted and might againe want the Subſidy of the ſame to her great loſſe. <note n="(d)" place="margin">Her Maieſties pleaſure that all the new ſorts of Draperies and Clothes ſhould at all times bee ſurueyed, meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, weighed, tried and ſealed, &amp;c.</note> Wherefore min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and intending redreſſe and remedie to bee had in that behalfe, her Maieſtie then thought good, and her will and pleaſure had beene ſignified by her former Letters Patents, and then was that all the ſaid new ſortes of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries, and Clothes aboue particularly ſpecified and expreſſed, and euery of them made, &amp; to be made, within this her Realme of England, and all other ſorts of woollen Clothes, new Draperies, made and to be made within this ſaid Realme, of wooll, or the moſt part of wooll, which in the time of her Raigne, or late before had not beene vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually made within this ſaid Realme of England, or for the which the ſaid Alnagers had not commonly vſed before that time, to make any ſearch, meaſure, weighing, marking or ſealing, or to take the ſaid Subſidie, ſhould at all times from thencefoorth be ſurueyed, meaſured, weighed, tryed and ſealed by ſuch perſon and perſons, as by the Lord <hi>Treaſurer</hi> of England for the time being, ſhould be from time to time appointed. <note n="(e)" place="margin">That the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie ſhould bee leuied and payd for the ſame from thencefoorth.</note> And that the ſaid Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie ſhould be leuied and paide for the ſame, from thencefoorth. And that for aſmuch, as her ſaid truſtie ſeruants Sir <hi>George Delues,</hi> and <hi>William Fitz-william,</hi> &amp; either of them Alnager &amp; Alnagers of the ſaid new Draperies, and Collectors of the ſaid Subſidie of the ſame, for and during the ſpace of xxi. yeeres, to commence and beginne at the Feaſt of the Natiuitie of S. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> then laſt paſt before the date of the ſame Letters Patents by themſelues their Deputies and Aſſignes. <note n="(f)" place="margin">The Queens Maieſties autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to her Alna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to weigh, meaſure, trye, ſearch and ſeale or marke all the new ſorts of dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries.</note> And her ſaid Maieſtie did thereby, for her, her heyres, and Succeſſors, giue and graunt vnto the ſaid Sir <hi>George Delues</hi> and <hi>William Fitz-william,</hi> their Executors, Adminiſtrators, and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and euery of them, full power and authoritie to weigh, meaſure, trie, ſearch and ſeale, or marke, all and ſingular the ſaid double, middle, and ſingle Bayes, Raſhe, or Stammell of Florence ſort, Serge of the French ſort Sayes of the Flanders ſort, Narrow Worſteeds, Grograynes, Mockadoes of euery ſort, Plummets, Freezadoes, Carrell, Fuſtians, called Fuſtians of Naples, Blankets, called Spaniſh Rugges, Knit-hoſe, and all and euery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new ſorts of Draperies or Clothes, and other Stuffes made or to be made only, or moſt part of wooll within this Realme of England, which in the time of her Raigne or late before, had not beene vſually made within this ſaid Realme of England, or for, or of the which the ſaid Alnagers for the time being, had not commonly before that
<pb facs="tcp:28718:2"/>
time vſed, to make any ſearch, meaſure, weighing, marking, or ſealing, or to take the ſayd Subſidies. <note n="(g)" place="margin">To haue and to hold during the ſpace of 21. yeeres.</note> To haue and to hold to them the ſame from the feaſt of the Natiuitie of Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> then laſt paſt, for and during the ſpace of one and twenty yeeres, from thence next enſuing, with authoritie and full power to ſeale and marke ſuch of the ſayd Draperies and ſtuffes as were and ſhould be lawfully and truely made, And with ſuch ſeale and ſeales or other marke, as by her High Treaſurer of England for the time being, ſhould bee deliuered and appointed to them for the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">Her Maieſty willed they ſhuld be reputed, taken and called Alna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the new draperies, &amp;c.</note>And whereas alſo, her ſaid Maieſtie, by her ſaid Letters Patents, did for her, her Heyres &amp; Succeſſors, will and graunt that during the ſaid Tearme of one and twentie yeares, they ſhould bee reputed, taken and called Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagers, Sealers, Searchers and Viewers of the new Draperies, and woollen commodities made, and to be made within this ſaid realme, and the Collectors of the Subſidies and duties thereof. <note n="(i)" place="margin">Her Maieſties command that at the new drape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries which were put to ſale, ſhould be meaſured, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſearched and weighed, and ſuch as were found good and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantable ſhould bee ſealed</note> And whereas alſo her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe did further of her certeine knowledge and meere motion graunt will and commaund, That euery of the ſaide Frezadoes, double, middle, and ſingle Baies, Raſh, or Stamel of Florence ſort, Serdge of the French ſort, Worſteds, Grograines, Mockadoes, of euery ſort, Plumet, Carrels, Fuſtians, called Fuſtian of Naples, Buffins, Blankets called Spaniſh Rugges, knit hoſe of Worſted yarne, Iarſey yarne or other woollen, made and to bee made, within this ſaid Realme to be put to ſale, and all other of the ſayd Draperies, and ſtuffes, made &amp; to be made within the ſame Realme of England, being all, or the moſt part of Wooll as aforeſaid, to be put to ſale, ſhould be meaſured, ſearched, weighed, and tried, by the ſaid Sir <hi>George Delues,</hi> and <hi>William Fitz william</hi> and their Executors Deputies and Aſſignes, or by ſome or one of them, (during the ſayd ſpace of twentie and one yeeres,) before the ſame ſhould bee put to ſale, And that all ſuch of the ſame as ſhould be found to be good Lawfull and Marchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ware ſhould be ſealed or marked by them their Deputies, Factors or Aſſignes, by a Seale or marke to them to be appointed by the ſayd high Treaſurer of England as aforeſayd. <note n="(k)" place="margin">All ſuch dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries and ſtuffes being found to be defectiue or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfully made or wrought, ſhuld be cut and lagged to the intent no perſons ſhould be deceiued thereby.</note> And that ſuch of the ſame Draperies and ſtuffes, as ſhould be found by them their Deputies and Miniſters, Factors or Aſſignes or any of them, to be defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue or deceitfully made or brought ſhould bee cut and Iagged at both the ends, thereby to note the ſame defect and default without any ſeale, or other marke to be put to the ſame, to the intent that no perſon or perſons ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued thereby. And whereas alſo her Maieſtie, by her ſayd Letters Patents, Recyting further that foraſmuch as no certaine rate or ſumme of money was before the ſayd graunt then tofore made to the ſaid Sir <hi>George Delues</hi> and <hi>William Fitz-william</hi> as aforeſaid taken, or payd to her ſayd Maieſtie, or certainly ſet downe for the meaſuring, ſearching, trying and Subſidies of the ſayde Draperies and other ſtuffes as aforeſayd: the Contents whereof were diuers, did ſignifie her will and pleaſure, to bee as by her ſayd former graunts her ſayd Maieſtie had before ſignified, <hi>viz.</hi> That where, by her lawes and Statutes there had bene and then was allowed due and payd for the ſayde Subſidie to her ſayde Maieſtie for euery broad Clothe, which by the Statute of this Realme ought to weigh threeſcore and foure pounds, the ſumme of <note n="(l)" place="margin">4 d. in money fo<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> euery broad cloth which by Statute ought to weigh 64 pound weight, and 2. d. for euery halfe cloth.</note> foure pence in money, for euery halfe of ſuch Cloth two pence in money which amounteth to one farthing for euery foure pound weight of the ſame Cloth. <note n="(m)" place="margin">For meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ſearching, and ſealing of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery whole cloth, ob and for euery halfe cloth a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</note> And for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring, ſearching and ſealing of euery whole Cloth, one halfe peny to the Alnager for his fee, and for euery halfe Cloth one farthing. That therefore the Rates and ſummes of money as well for the Subſidie, as for the Alnage of the ſayd new Draperies, and other new wollen commodities particularly and otherwiſe ſpecified, or contained in a Schedule vnto the ſaid Letters Patents annexed, ſhould bee paid allowed and leuied from thencefoorth, of and for euery of the ſayd new Draperies which was found to agree or not much to differ in proportion, from the Rates and Duties, ſet payd and allowed then-tofore for broad wollen Cloathes. And that if any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of what eſtate or degree ſoeuer he or they ſhould bee, did ſell or put to ſale, or cauſe to be ſold or put to ſale, or ſhould fraught or imbarque or cauſe to be ſhipped, fraughted, or imbarqued any of the new ſaid Draperies, or wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, or ſuch ſtuffes as is aforeſaid in the ſaid Letters Patents authoriſed to be ſearched, to the intent to Tranſport the ſame to be put to ſale before the ſame ſhould bee ſearched, meaſured, weighed, and ſealed by her Maieſties ſayd Officers, or their Aſſignes as aforeſayd, And the fees and Subſidies aforeſayd therefore payd or agreed for, That then and ſo often, as hee, ſhe, or they ſo putting to ſale, ſhipping, lading, fraughting or imbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quing the ſame ſhould <note n="(n)" place="margin">To forfeyt xx.s. for vttering or putting to ſale, ſhipping, lading, or fraughting e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie piece be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were firſt ſearched, meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſealed.</note> forfeit and pay for euery piece thereof ſo put to ſale or offered to bee put to ſale, ſhipped, fraughted or imbarqued, twenty ſhillings of lawfull money of England. And where alſo her ſayd late Maieſty by her ſayd Letters Patents of her further eſpeciall grace, meere motion and certaine knowledge did demiſe and grant to farme, to the ſaid Sir <hi>George Delues,</hi> and <hi>William Fitz-william</hi> their Executors and Aſſignes, the Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſummes and duties limitted by the ſayd Letters Pattents to be payd of or for all and euery the ſaid new Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries and other woollen Commodities aforeſayd, And all and euery the forfeytures afore ſayd, as to her Maieſty, her Heires and Succeſſors, ſhould grow anſwerable or due: To haue and to hold the ſayd Subſidie, ſummes, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and forfeytures to the ſayd Sir <hi>George Delues,</hi> and <hi>William Fitz-william</hi> their Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſignes, from the feaſt of the Natiuitie of Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> then laſt paſt before the date of the ſayde Letters Patents vnto the end and terme of one and twenty yeeres, from thence, next enſuing, and fully to be Compleat and ended, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">The woolles of the Realme from time to time conuerted not onely into ſtuffes, draperies and commodities: but alſo into diuers other new ſorts of ſtuffes, not made within this Realme at the time of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties grant to Sir George Delues, &amp; William Fitz-william, to the great loſſe of his Maieſties Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies in former times payd for the woolles of this Land tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, &amp;c.</note>And whereas we perceiuing the Woolles of this Realme to be from time to time conuerted not onely into the Stuffes, Draperies, &amp; Commodities aboue mentioned, but alſo into diuers other new ſortes of Stuffes, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries and Commodities not made within this Realme, at the time of the making of the ſayde ſeuerall Leaſes or grants to the ſayd Sir <hi>George Delues,</hi> and <hi>William Fitz-william,</hi> to Our great loſſe in the Cuſtomes and Subſidies, in former times payd to diuers of Our Progenitors, for the Woolles of this Land tranſported into the parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, and that the ſame new inuentions are likely more and more to increaſe: And perceiuing alſo that diuers Clothiers heretofore vſing to make broad Clothes, haue changed their Loomes, and ſpinnings to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſame new inuentions, And that it is to bee preſumed that others will doe the like: The game and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of ſuch new Draperies and late inuented ſtuffes, and Commodities, made of Wooll, or part of Wooll com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring weight to weight being farre greater and quicker, and the trade thereof exerciſed with leſſe ſtocke &amp; charge then is requiſite to the making of broad Clothes, which would turne greatly to Our loſſe, if as well a Subſidie ſhould not be payd and anſwered vnto Vs for the ſaid new Inuentions as for broad Clothes. We well approuing our ſayd Siſters care and prouiſion that proportionable ſummes ſhould be paid for the Subſidie and Alnage of the ſayd new and later Inuentions, according to the rate of the Subſidie and Alnage payd for broad Cloth: are fully minded and purpoſed, And doe by theſe preſents appoint, That as by the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme, there hath beene and now is allowed due and payd to Vs for the Subſidie of euery broad Cloth made to bee ſold, which by the Statutes of this Realme ought to weigh threeſcore and foure pounds, The ſumme of foure pence in money, And for euery halfe of ſuch Cloth two pence in money which amounteth to one farthing for euery foure pound weight of the ſame Clothe. And for the meaſuring, ſearching, and ſealing of euery whole broad Clothe made to be ſold which by the Statutes of this Realme ought to containe in length foure and twenty yards, one halfe penny to the Alnager for his Fee, and for euery halfe of ſuch Cloth one farthing, ſo from henceforth for euery threeſcore and foure pound weight of the ſayd <note n="(p)" place="margin">4. d. for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie 64. pound weight of the ſaid Freezadoes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording and ſo ratably for euery ſuch king of new draperies</note> Freezadoes, double, middle &amp; ſingles Bayes, Raſh, or Stamel of Florence ſort, Serdge of French ſort, Sayes of the Flaunders ſort, Narrow Worſteds, Valentia, Grograines,
<pb facs="tcp:28718:3"/>
and Grograines of all ſorts,<note place="margin">The names of ſtuffes belonging to the new dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie.</note> Mockadoes of euery ſort, Plummets, Carrell, Fuſtians, and Fuſtian called Fuſtian of Naples, Buffins of all ſorts, Blankets, called Spaniſh Rugges, knit hoſe of Woorſted yarne, Iarſey yarne or other woollen yarne, And for euery threeſcore and foure pound weight of all ſorts of the woollen and party wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Clothes, ſtuffes, &amp; Commodities of Arras, Tapeſſary or Tapiſtry, Abrecetta, Bewpars, Boratoes, Boulters, Blanckets, Buſteans, Bombacies, Brocatellaes, Calimancoes, Cangeans, changeable Canuas, Channo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clothes, Chamblets, Carſa, Criſpe, Crewel, Carpetings, Couerlets, Curles, Dornix, Duraunces, Damaſks <hi>Demicie,</hi> Faire a farre off, Fuſtenadoes of all ſorts, Fringe, Felts, Flannels, Garterings, Gyrthes, Girdlings, knit waſtcotes, knit petticotes, knit ſleeues, knit Gloues, knit Caps, knit Coyfes, knit Hats, knit ſocks, Lyon Raſſhes, Lacyngs, Lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy Wolſeys, Maſſalina, Macrels, Moheres, Mountaines, Mounkes Clothes, Motleis, Minikins, Oſetts, Oly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots, Parris clothes, Pomets, Perpetuanaes, Perpinianes, Spaniſh pretitoes, Quinques, Raſhes, Cloth Raſhes, Ruſſels, Rugges, Raynes of bridles, Spaniſh Sattens, Sattens of Cyprus, Serdges, Sayes, Stamels, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets, Stammes, Swaithbands, Sparke of Veluet, Spaniſh Cloth, Sciets, Scallops, Tukes, Tamets, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bynes, Twilles, Thrumes, Velures, Venice Cloth, Worſteeds, Wadinols, yarne of Worſted, Iarſey or wollen, and of all other ſorts of Clothes, Stuffes, Draperies and Commodities whatſoeuer, made or hereafter to be made within the Realme of England and Dominion of Wales, to bee ſold of wooll, part of wooll, Cotton woollen or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe: which in the time of our late Siſters Raigne, or late before had not beene vſually made within this Realme of England or Dominion of Wales, or of or for the which the Alnagers of ſaleable Clothes, did not before that time commonly vſe to make any ſearch, meaſure, weighing, marking or ſealing, or to take the ſaid Subſidie: ſhall be from time to time anſwered and paid to vs our Heires and Succeſſors by the Sellers of the ſaide Clothes, Stuffes, Draperies and Commodities, the ſumme of foure pence for and in the name of a Subſidie, And ſo rata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie for euery ſuch kind of Clothes, Stuffes, Draperies, and Commodities, according to the ſeuerall weight, and weights of the ſame. And for the ſearching, meaſuring, and marking, or ſealing of euery peece of ſuch Cloth, Stuffe, or Draperie, containing in length foure and twentie yards, or betweene foure and twentie and thirtie yards, or leſſe, ſhall be paid to the Alnager thereof for his Fee, the ſumme of one halfe peny, And ſo ratably for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery peece, of like Cloth, Stuffe, and other Draperies and Commodities aforeſaid, according to the number of the yards, and quantitie that it ſhall containe.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as our right truſtie, and right intirely beloued Cozen and Counſellor <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nox</hi> hath procured the ſaid Letters Patents therof made to the ſayd S. <hi>George Delues,</hi> &amp; <hi>William Fitz william</hi> to be <note n="(q)" place="margin">The patent g<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nted S<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to Ge<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rge Delues and W<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lliam Fitz-willi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ſu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rendered by the pr<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>curement of Lodowicke Duke of Lenox.</note> ſurrendred, And hath offered to take to Farme of vs the ſayd Subſidie, or ſumme of money herein before ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be paid to vs our Heires and Succeſſors, in the name of a Subſidie of and for all and euery the ſaid laſt mentioned Clothes, Stuffes, Draperies and commodities, made and hereafter to be made within this Realme of England and Dominion of Walles, to be ſould, (except ſuch as are and ſhall be made, or hereafter ſet to ſale in the Citie of London and the Suburbs and liberties of the ſame Citie,) And to yeeld and pay therefore vnto vs a greater yeerely rent, Farme or ſumme then hath beene heretofore anſwered and paid for the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">The creation of the Duke of Lenox, his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Alnager of all the new dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries.</note>Now, know yee that Wee of our ſpeciall grace certaine knowledge and meere motion haue Created, ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Conſtituted and appointed and by theſe preſents for vs our Heires and Succeſſors, create, ordaine, conſtitute and appoint the ſaid <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of <hi>Lenox</hi> our Alnager of all and euery the ſaid Freezadoes, double, middle &amp; ſingle Bayes, Raſh or Stamell of Florence ſort, Serge of the French ſort, Sayes of the Flaunders ſort, Narrow Worſteds, Valentia, Grograines &amp; Grograines of all ſorts, Mockadoes of euery ſort, Plumets, Carrell, Fuſtians, and Fuſtian called Fuſtian of Naples, Buffines of all ſorts, Blankets called Spaniſh Rugges, Knit hoſe of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed yarne, Iarſey yarne, or other woollen yarne, And for euery threeſcore and foure pound weight of all ſorts of the woollen and partie woollen Clothes, Stuffes and Commodities of Arras, Tapeſſary or Tapeſtrie, Abrecetta, Bewpars,<note place="margin">Names of all the Commodities.</note> Boratoes, Boulters, Blankets, Buſtians, Bumbacies, Brocatellaes, Callimancoes, Cangeans, chaungeable Canuas, Channon Clothes, Chamlets, Carfa, Criſpe, Crewell, Carpetings, Couerlets, Curles, Dornix, Duraunces, Damaſkes, Demicie, Faire a farre off, Fuſtenadoes of all ſorts, Fringe, Felts, Flannels, Garterings, Gyrthes, Gyrdlings, knit Waſtcotes, knit Petticotes, knit Sleeues, knit Gloues, knit Cappes, knit Coyfes, knit Hats, knit ſockes, Lyon Raſhes, Lacings, Lincey wolſeies. Maſſalina, Mackrels, Mohers, Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, Mounks Clothes, Motlies, Minikins, Oſets, Oliots, Parris Clothes, Pomets, Perpetuanaes. Perpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianes, Spaniſh pretitoes, Quinques, Raſhes, cloth Raſhes, Ruſſels Rugs, Raines of bridles, Spaniſh Sattens, Sattens of Cyprus, Serdges, Sayes, Stammels, Stamets, Stamynes, Swaithbands, Sparke a Veluet, Spaniſh Cloth, Scyets, Scallops, Tukes, Tamets, Tobynes, Twilles, Thrumes, Velures, Venice Cloth, Worſteeds, Wadnols, Yarne of worſteed, Iarſey or woolen, and of all other ſorts of Cloathes, Stuffes, Draperies &amp; Commodities whaſoeuer called or known by the name of New Draperie, or made or hereafter to be made within this our Realme of England and Dominion of Wales, (Except ſuch as are and ſhall bee made or hereafter ſet to ſale in the Citie of London and the Suburbes and Liberties of the ſame Citie,) by whatſoeuer name or names the ſame is, are, or ſhall be knowen or called to be ſould of wooll, part of wooll, Cotten wooll or otherw<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe which in the time of our late Siſters Raigne, or late before had not beene uſually made within this Realme of England or Dominion of Wales, or of or for the which the Alnagers of ſaleable Cloathes did not before that time common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe to make any ſearch, meaſure, weighing, marking, or ſealing, or to take the ſaid Subſidie.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">The Duke of Lenox his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Collector of the Subſidie for the new dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries.</note>And of our further eſpeciall grace, certaine knowledge, and meere motion, we haue created, ordained, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted and appointed, and by theſe Preſents doe created, ordaine, conſtitute and appoint the ſaid <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke <hi>Lenox</hi> of our Collector of the ſaid Subſidie, and ſumme or ſummes of money herein before appointed to be paid to vs, our Heires and Succeſſors in the name of a ſubſidie, of and for all and euery the ſaid Freezadoes, double, mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and ſingle Bayes, Raſhe or Stammell of Florence ſort, Serdge of the French ſort, Sayes of the Flaunders ſort, Narrow Worſteeds, Valentia Grograines, and Grograines of all ſorts, Mockadoes, of euery ſort, Plumets, Carrell, Fuſtians, and Fuſtian called Fuſtian of Naples, Buffynes of all ſorts, Blankets, called Spaniſh Rugges, knit hoſe of worſted Yarne, Iarſey Yarne, or other woollen Yarne, And for euery threeſcore and foure pound weight of all ſorts of the woollen, &amp; partie woollen Clothes, ſtuffes &amp; commodities, Abracetta, Arras, Tapeſſarie, or Tapeſtry, Bewpars, Boratoes, Bowlters, Blankets, Buſteans, Bumbacies, Brocatelloes, Calimancoes, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geans, Chaungeable Canuis, Channon clothes, Chamlets, Carſa, Criſpe, Crewell, Carpetings, Couerlettes, Curles, Dornix, Durances, Damaſkes, Dimicie, Faire a farre off, Fuſtenadoes of all ſorts, Fringe, Feltes, Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, Garterings, Girthes, Girdlings, Knit Waſtcotes, knit Petticotes, knit Sleeues, knit Gloues, knit Caps, knit Coifes, knit Hats, knit Sockes, Lyon Raſhes, Lacings, Lincey Wolſies, Maſſalina, Makrelles, Moheres, Mountaynes, Mounkes Clothes, Motlies, Minikins, Oſets, Oleots, Paris Clothes, Pomets, Perpetuanaes, Perpinianes, Spaniſh Pretitoes, Quinques, Raſhes, Cloth Raſhes, Ruſſelles, Rugs, Raines of bridles, Spaniſh Sattynes, Sattynes of Ciprus, Serdges, Sayes, Stammels, Stamets, Stamines, Swaithbands, Sparke of veluet, Spaniſh Cloath, Scyets, Scallopes, Tukes, Tamets, Tobynes, Twillies, Thrumes, Velures, Venice cloth worſteds, Wadmolles, Yarne of worſted Iarſey or woollen, and of all other ſorts of clothes, Stuffes, Drape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and commodities whatſoeuer, made or hereafter to be made within this Realme of England, &amp; Dominion of Wales, (Except ſuch as are and ſhall be made, or hereafter ſet to ſale in the Citie of London, and the Suburbes
<pb facs="tcp:28718:4"/>
and Liberties of the ſame Citie) made, or to be made of wooll, part of wooll, Cotten wooll, or otherwiſe as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid to the intent to be ſould, which in the time of our ſaide late Siſters Raigne or late before had not beene vſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made within this Realme of England, or Dominion of Wales, or of, or for the which the Alnagers of ſaleable Clothes, did not before that time commonly vſe to make any ſearch, meaſure, weighing, marking or ſealing, or to take the ſaid Subſidie.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(t)" place="margin">His Maieſties grant to the duke of Lenox of the office of Alnager and Collector of the Subſidie of new Draperies.</note>And we doe by theſe preſents for vs our Heires and Succeſſors, giue and grant to the ſaid <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox, his Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſignes, and euery of them the office and offices of Alnager, and of Collector of the Subſidie of the ſaid clothes, ſtuffes, draperies and commodities, with all lawfull Fees, Benefits and profits, whatſoeuer therto belonging (except before excepted,) &amp; full power liberty and authoritie by him or themſelues, his or their Deputie or Deputies, or Aſſignes, to exerciſe and execute the ſame Offices, and to weigh, meaſure, trie, ſearch, and ſeale or marke, all and ſingular the ſayd clothes, ſtuffes, draperies, and Commodities made and to be made, within this our Realme of England, and Dominion of Wales, (except before excepted) of, or for the which the ſaid Subſidie is herein aboue appointed to be paid, or which bee hereby authoriſed to bee ſearched.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">Arrerages due from Mich. 2. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acobi R <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>null 16. Nouem 3. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi R together with the ſaid of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice granted to the duke his exec. admin. aſſig dep. an this and their lawfull d<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>puties for 21. yeeres.</note>And further, we do by theſe Preſents of our ſpeciall grace, certaine knowledge and meere motion giue and grant vnto the ſaid <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox, his executors, adminiſtrators deputies &amp; aſſignes, all &amp; euery ſuch arrerages, duties, ſum and ſums of money whatſoeuer, as are due and payable for the ſaid office of Alnage and Subſidie, and other the premiſſes, ſince the Feaſt of S. <hi>Michael</hi> th'archangell now laſt paſt, vntill the day of the date of theſe Preſents, To haue and to holde, exerciſe and enioy the ſaid Offices, with the ſaid arrerages, duties and premiſſes vnto the ſayde <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox, his Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſignes, and his and their lawfull Deputie and Deputies, from the Feaſt of S. <hi>Michael</hi> th'archangel laſt paſt before the date hereof, for and during the ſpace of one and twentie yeeres, from thence next following with authoritie, and full power to ſeale, and marke ſuch of the ſaid Clothes, Draperies, Stuffes, and Commodities, as be and ſhall be lawfully and truely made with ſuch ſeale and ſeales, or other marke, as by our high Treaſurer of Endland for the time being, ſhall be deliuered and appointed to him or them for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">His Maieſties pleaſure &amp; grant that the ſaid duke of Lenox during the ſpace of 21. yeeres. Shall be reputed taken &amp; called Alnager, ſeal<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, ſearcher, and viewer of all the new D<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and Collector of the Su<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſid<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es and dueties for the ſame.</note>And our will and pleſure is, and we doe for vs, our heires and ſucceſſors, grant by theſe preſents, That du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſayd ſpace of one and twentie yeres, the ſaid <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox, ſhall be reputed, named, taken and called Alnager, Sealer, Searcher and viewer of the ſaid new Draperies, and woollen commodities and Stuffes, made, or hereafter to bee made within this our Realme of England, and Dominion of Wales, (except before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted,) and the Collector of the Subſidies and dueties thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(y)" place="margin">His Maieſties command that all new Draperies within the Realm of England and Dominion of Wales, ſhall be meaſured, ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, weighed, and tried by the ſaid Duke, his depu. or aſſig or his or their depu. or aſſig.</note>And we doe further of our certaine knowledge and meere motion graunt, will and commaund, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the ſayd clothes, ſtuffes, draperies and commodities by whatſoeuer name or names, they are, or ſhall bee knowen, or called, made, and hereafter to be made within this our Realme of England, and Dominion of Wales, (except before excepted) to be put to ſale. And all other of the ſaid Draperies, Stuffes and Commodities, called new Draperies, or dewly heretofore inuented, or hereafter to be inuented, made and to be made within the ſame our Realme of England, and Dominion of Wales (except before excepted) being all or part of wooll, or otherwiſe as aforeſaid, to be put to ſale, ſhall be during the ſaid ſpace and terme of one and twentie yeeres, meaſured, ſearched, weighed and tried by the ſaid <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox, his Executors, Adminiſtrators, Deputies and Aſſignes, and his or their Deputie or Deputies, or by ſome or one of them, before the ſame ſhall be put to ſale.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">And being found to be good lawfull and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantable, to be ſealed or marked.</note>And that all ſuch of the ſame as ſhall be found to be good, lawfull and marchantable ware, ſhall be ſealed or marked by our ſaid Alnager, his Executors, Adminiſtrators, Deputies, and Aſſignes, or his or their Deputie or Deputies, by and with a ſeale or marke to him or them to be appointed by our ſaid high Treaſurer of England as aforeſaid. <note n="(a)" place="margin">His Maieſties pleaſure that no perſon ſhall ſell, ſet, ſend, or put to ſale, or Shippe, Fraight or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barke any the ſaid new Draperies to the intent to tranſport the ſame to be put to ſale before they be ſearched, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, weighed &amp; ſealed or marked by the Alnager his exec. admin. depu or aſſig. and the Fees and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies paid there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or agreed for, vpon paine of forf<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>iture of 20.5. for euery ſuch peece of ſtuffe.</note> And that ſuch of the ſame Clothes, Draperies, Stuffes and Commodities as aforeſaide, as ſhall bee found by our ſaide Alnager, his Deputies, Miniſters, Factors or Aſſignes, or his or their Deputie or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, or any of them, to be Defectiue or Deceitfuly made or wrought, ſhall bee by him or them cut and iagged at both the ends, thereby to note the ſame defect and default without any ſeale or other marke to be put to the ſame, to the intent that no perſon or perſons be deceiued thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Authoritie that all ſuch of the ſame clothes Draperies, Stuffes being found to be defectiue or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully made or wrought ſhould be cut and iag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged at both ends without any ſeale thereto, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be deceiued thereby.</note>And our will and pleaſure is, that if any perſon or perſons of what eſtate or degree ſoeuer, hee or they bee of, doe or ſhall ſell, ſet, ſend, or put to ſale, or cauſe to bee ſold, ſent, ſet, or put to ſale, or doe or ſhall Fraught, or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barque, or cauſe to bee Shipped, Fraughted, or Imbarqued, any of the ſaid Clothes, Stuffes, Draperies and Commodities, or any other ſuch like, as is aforſaid herein authoriſed to be ſearched and ſealed, to the intent to tranſport the ſame to be put to ſale, before the ſame ſhall be ſearched, meaſured, weighed and ſealed, or marked by our ſaid Officer, his Executors, Adminiſtrators, Deputies or Aſſignes as aforeſaid, and the Fees and Subſidies, aforeſaid therefore payed or agreed for, That then and ſo often, hee, ſhee, or they, ſo ſelling, ſending, ſetting or put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to ſale, Shipping, Lading, Fraughting or Imbarking the ſame, ſhall forfeite and pay for euery peece there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo ſold, ſent, ſet or put to ſale, or offered to be put to ſale, Shipped, Fraughted, or Embarqued, twentie ſhillings of lawfull money of England.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">His Maieſties demiſe for 21. yeeres to the Duke, of all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies, ſummes &amp; duties, limited to be paid for the new Draperies &amp; the moietie of all and euery the forfeitures.</note>And further, know ye that of Our further eſpeciall grace, certaine knowledge and meere motion, we haue demiſed and granted, and by theſe preſents doe demiſe and grant to farme to the ſayd <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox, his executors, adminiſtrators, and Aſſignes, the ſubſidies, ſummes and dueties, limitted by theſe preſents, to bee payd of, or for all and euery the ſayd new Draperies, ſtuffes and other woollen commodities, aforeſayd made and to be made within this our Realme of England and dominion of Wales (except before excepted,) and the Moyetie of all and euery the forfeyture and forfeytures aforeſayd, as to Vs Our Heyres and Succeſſours due or ſhall grow anſwerable or due. To haue and to hold the ſayd Subſidie, ſummes, duties and moyeties of forfeytures, of all and euery the ſayd Clothes, ſtuffes, draperies and commodities vnto the ſayd <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox, his executors, adminiſtrators and aſſignes from the ſayd Feaſt of S. <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel laſt paſt, vnto the end and terme of one and twenty yeeres, from thence next enſuing, and fully to be complete and ended.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">The ſame new Draperies, Stuffes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities being once ſearched, meaſured &amp; ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or marked by the Duke, or his depu. ſeruants or aſſig. ſhall not any more be ſearched, meaſured, ſealed, or marked by any other.</note>And further, our will and pleaſure is, and we doe by theſe preſents graunt, That whatſoeuer of the ſayd new Draperies, ſtuffes, and commodities, ſhall be by the ſayd <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox, his deputies, ſeruants, or aſſignes, or by any of them ſearched, meaſured and ſealed, or marked in forme aforeſayd, the ſame ſhal not after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards for the ſame cauſe be by any other our Officers, Miniſters or ſubiects, within this our realme of England or Dominion of Wales (except before excepted) any more ſearched, meaſured, ſealed or marked, but that the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the ſame may frankly and freely ſell, vtter or marchandize the ſame to any perſon or perſons, without any maner of other charge, vexation, impeachment, moleſtation or interruption whatſoeuer, for or concerning the ſaid Subſidie and alnage before expreſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Authoritie granted to the Duke &amp; his dep. to appoint in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry county or other places ſufficient dep. for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the ſaid offices.</note>And further for the better execution of the ſayd offices, and of theſe our Letters Patents, of our like eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall grace, meere motion, and certaine knowledge, wee doe by theſe Preſentes for vs, our heires and ſucceſſors, giue and graunt vnto the ſayd <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox, his executors adminiſtrators and aſſignes, and to his and their deputie and deputies, full power and lawfull authoritie, to conſtitute, ſubſtitute, make and appoint
<pb facs="tcp:28718:5"/>
in euery or any of the Counties, Cities, Townes corporate, Boroughs, Townes, Villages and Hamlets within this our Realme of England, and dominion of Wales (except before excepted) ſuch and ſo many ſufficient ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and deput<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, for the meaſuring, ſearching, viewing, weighing, marking and ſealing of all ſuch Clothes, Draperies, ſtuffes and commodities, as are heerein or heereby appointed, or authoriſed to be meaſured, ſearched, viewed, weighed, marked or ſealed; And for the collection and gathering of the ſayd ſubſidies and Alnage, as by the ſayd <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox, his executors, adminiſtrators or aſſignes ſhall be thought meete and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, and to the ende and intent, to auoyd all fraudes and deceits, and all concealements of, in, and about the Premiſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Authoritie at all reaſonable times, to enter into all places whatſoeuer, to ſearch, ſee and trie, &amp;c. If any the ſayd new dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries ſhall bee ſent or put to ſale, &amp;c. before they be ſealed or marked, and the ſome to keepe ſeize and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, &amp;c.</note>We do further giue and grant by theſe Preſents, for vs our heyres and ſucceſſors, vnto the ſayd <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox, his executors, adminiſtrators and aſſignes, and his and their Deputie and Deputies, and euery of them, full power and lawfull authoritie, at all reaſonable times and in reaſonable maner, without vnneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hurting of any perſon or perſons, or any their goods, wares, or marchandiſe, to enter into all and euery faires, markets, houſes, milles, ſhops, warehouſes, Ships, Barkes, Crayers, Boats, and all other places whatſoeuer, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well within Liberties as without, within our ſayd Realme of England, and Dominion of Wales, (except before excepted) and to ſearch, ſee, trie and examine, if any of the ſayd Clothes, ſtuffes, Draperies, or Commodities, and all other the ſayd new draperies, &amp; new deuiſes, and other ſtuffes as aforeſayd, or any of them made or hereafter to be made of wooll, part of wooll, cotton wool, or otherwiſe as aforeſayd, ſhal be ſent, put or ſet to ſale, vttered, ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped or imbarqued, being not before ſealed or marked by our ſaid Alnager his executors, adminiſtrators or aſſignes, or his or their deputie or deputies, or one of them with the ſeale or marke thereunto ordained, contrary to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of theſe preſents, and ſuch of the ſayd Clothes, Draperies, ſtuffes, and new inuented and deuiſed commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as ſhall bee by him or them found to be ſent, put, or ſet to ſale, ſhipped or imbarqued, not marqued or ſealed as aforeſaid, to ſeize, keepe, and retaine, till the forfeiture and forfeytures aforeſayd, and euery of them ſhall bee fully and wholly ſatiſfied and payd according to the intent and true meaning of theſe Preſents, or other order taken therein by the Lord Treſurer of England for the time being, and Our Court of Exchequer.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">That if any perſon or perſons ſhal reſiſt or deny any ſearch, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit for euery ſuch default, 10. lib.</note>And that if any perſon or perſons ſhall reſiſt or denie any ſuch ſearch or ſearches by Our ſayd Alnager, his Officers, Deputies or aſſignes, or his or their deputies or aſſignes, from time to time to be made, That then he, ſhee, or they making reſiſtance or deniall, ſhall for euery ſuch default, forfeyt and pay to Vs and Our Heires and Succeſſors, ten pounds of lawfull Engliſh money.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">Expreſſe command that no Cuſtomers, Comptrolers, or Collectors, of the Subſidies of <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage or pondage, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r doe take any <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utie, receiue any cuſt<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me, or m<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e com<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> they <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſeale<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by the Alna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or his Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note>And We doe heereby further wil and Command that none of our Cuſtomers, Comptrollers, or Collectors of Our Subſidies of Tonnage or Pondage in any Our Cuſtome-houſes in any Port within our Realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land or Dominion of Wales (except before excepted) or of any of Our Farmers of the ſame Cuſtomes or Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, of Tonnage or Pondage, or any of their Officer or Officers, doe from hencefoorth, take any entrie or receiue any Cuſtome or Subſidie, or make any compoſition for any Cuſtome or Subſidie for any the ſayd Clothes, ſtuffes, Draperies or Commodities whatſoeuer made or hereafter to be made within our Realme of England and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Wales, (except before excepted) vnleſſe they be ſealed or marked by our ſayd Alnager, his Executors, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators or Aſſignes, or his or their Deputie or Deputies, or one of them with the Seale or marke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ordained.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">His Maieſties expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement to all, &amp;c. to be ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and aſſiſting in the execution of this office, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e of his Highnes diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and as they will anſwere the contrarie at their perils.</note>And our further will and pleaſure is, and we doe ſtraightly Charge and Command, all and euery Maiors, Sheriffes, Bailiffes, Iuſtices of Peace, head Boroughs, Conſtables, and other Our Officers, Miniſters, and Subiects whatſoeuer, That they ayde and aſſiſt, the ſaid <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox his Executors, Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Aſſignes, and his or their Deputie or Deputies, and euery of them, in and by all lawfull meanes, and wayes whatſoeuer for the due execution of the foreſayd Offices, and theſe Our Letters Patents, according to the forme, force, and effect thereof, as they tender Our pleaſure, and will anſwere to the contrary at their perils.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Authoritie to the lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of England for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to make new and further ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and to graunt command for the further aid and aſſiſtance in the execution of the ſaid office and his Maieſties letters Patents.</note>And further of Our certaine knowledge, and meere motion, wee grant will and Command, that if there ſhall want any ſufficient Act, meane, or thing, to giue ſufficient power and authoritie to Our ſayd Officer his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors, Adminiſtrators, Deputies, and Aſſignes, and to the Deputies and Aſſignes of euery of them, to doe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and execute all and euery or any thing mentioned in theſe preſents, according to the true meaning and effect thereof, for the aduancement of the ſayde Office, and Farme which is meant to Our ſpeciall benefit: That the Lord Treaſurer of England for the time being, ſhall from time to time haue power and authoritie to make new and further Ordinances, and to graunt Commiſſions for the further ayde, and aſſiſtance of our ſayd Couſin <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of Lenox, his Executors, Adminiſtrators, Deputies, and Aſſignes, in and for the full Execution and performance of the ſayd Offices and of theſe Our Letters Patents.</p>
            <p>In witneſſe whereof Wee haue cauſed theſe Our Letters to be made Patents. Witneſſe Our ſelfe at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, the ſixteenth day of September, in the third yeere of Our Reigne of England, Fraunce, and Ireland, and of Scotland the nine and thirtieth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Clapham. Per bre. de priuat. Sigil.</signed>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
